Guide to the Printmaker File [1730]-present, (bulk 1800-1860) PR 58
© 2011 New-York Historical Society
Printmaker File
[1730]-present (bulk 1800-1860)
PR 58
© 2011 New-York Historical Society
2.375 Linear feet (ca. 500 prints)
The Printmaker File is comprised of prints which are filed by the artist or engraver. It includes aquatints, engravings, etchings, lithographs, and woodcuts. These prints are likely to be known or studied because of their creators or because of their significance in the history of American printmaking
Provenance
This collection is comprised of gifts from multiple donors, and several purchases.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers.
Photocopying undertaken by staff only. Limited to twenty exposures of stable, unbound material per day. See guidelines in Print Room for details.
Scope and Content Note
The Printmaker File spans the period from the 1730s to the 1990s and contains etchings, engravings, aquatints, and lithographs, mainly views of New York City and the east coast of the United States.
Historically, many items acquired by the Department of Prints, Photographs, and Architectural Collections were filed by subject or geographical location. Prints were housed in the Printmaker File if the importance of the artist or printmaker was deemed more important than the subject or place. For example, fine art prints of geographical locations were filed here instead of in the Geographic File. In many cases (i.e. Louis Prang, Bufford's Lithography) there are other prints by printmakers represented here in different collections throughout the Department. This file reflects a historical way of organizing prints, and now creates a backbone for any future filing by printmaker.
In addition, prints are filed here if they are considered to be "fine art," or notable in some way, but do not correspond to another kind of collection. For example, Lou Barlow, a WPA printmaker, has a few prints of New York scenes in the Fine Art Prints of New York City collection; several other of his prints (a self-portrait, a few non-New York views) are included here.
"Printmaker" generally means the engraver, etcher, or lithographer of a print. In some cases it refers to the publisher of a print or to the original artist. In all cases, any other known names associated with the print (i.e. original artist, sketch designer, publisher) are given here. Lithographs found in this file are generally notable for their early dates. Lithography firms such as Bufford's Lithography and H. N. Sumner & Co. are considered the "printmaker," as is Jacques-Gerard Milbert, who did not actually draw on stone many of the views after his work found in this File.
Many prints collected here are remarkable for their age, their provenance, or their historical significance. Early views of New York City, Savannah, Georgia, and Charlestown, South Carolina can be found in the File. However, there are also a fair amount of twentieth-century prints.
The collection is arranged into three series by size of print, to ensure correct handling and housing of the material: Series I. Prints 16 x 20" and smaller; Series II. Prints 16 x 20" to 30 x 40"; Series III. Prints larger than 30 x 40". Print titles are taken from inscriptions where possible. Titles given in brackets were assigned during processing.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into three series by size of print. Thereunder prints are arranged alphabetically by printmaker's surname.
Series I. Prints 16 x 20" and smaller
Series II. Prints 16 x 20" to 30 x 40"
Series III. Prints larger than 30 x 40"
Related Material at the Department of Prints, Photographs, and Architectural Collections
Fine art prints with a subject of New York City can be found in the James Boyd Collection of New York City Etchings (PR 007,) and in the Fine Art Prints of New York City file (PR 229.)
Separated Material
At the time of cataloging, several groups of prints were removed from this collection and established as discrete collections. These are:
PR 162 Audubon Print Collection
PR 216 Alexander Anderson Print Collection
PR 220 William James Bennett Print Collection
PR 230 Currier and Ives Print File
PR 221 Asher B. Durand Print Collection
PR 217 John Hill Print Collection
PR 225 Anthony Imbert Print Collection
PR 226 James King Print Collection
PR 224 Peter Maverick Print File
PR 227 Saint-Memin Print Collection
Bufford's Lithographs (New York); Burgis, William, fl. 1722-1736; Davis, Alexander Jackson, 1803-1892; Doolittle, Amos, 1754-1832; H.F. Sumner & Co.; Hoff, Henry; Milbert, Jacques Gérard, 1766-1840; Revere, Paul, 1735-1818; Sandby, Paul, 1731-1809; Whistler, James McNeill, 1834-1903; Woodcut Society (Kansas City, Mo.); Adirondack Mountains (N.Y.); Aquatints; Boston Massacre, 1770; Engravings; Etchings; Lithographs; Mezzotints; New York (N.Y.) -- Description and travel; New York (State) -- Description and travel; Prints; Savannah (Ga.); United States -- Description and travel; Woodcuts
- Series I: Prints 16 x 20" and smaller
  Scope and Contents note
  Series I. Prints 16 x 20" and smaller, is arranged alphabetically by artist or printmaker's surname. These prints are housed in boxes. Not all prints are item-level described here. See the box listing for a complete list of all printmakers.
  The [Views of the Adirondack Mountain Region], lithographed by John Henry Bufford and published by Bufford's Lithography were commissioned to illustrate the New York State Assembly Document no. 200 which was written in 1837 by several geologists after an expedition to the Adirondack region; here the term "Adirondacks" was first used. These prints are thus notable in that they are the first to show views of the Adirondacks under that name. The complete set of ten lithographed views and five engraved maps was issued separately from the Document in paper covers. Some prints are after painter Charles Cromwell Ingham
  "View of Fort George" (1730-1731), attributed to William Burgis, is the first known engraved view of New York City from the west and the first mezzotint view of the city. This is a unique print, and is enclosed in an eighteenth-century, but not original, frame. John Carwitham's "View of Fort George with the City of New York from the S.W.," itself an early and important view of New York, is based on Burgis' view.
  The illustrated broadside, with a woodcut by S. Burnet of the horse Grand Seignior, is considered to be an early image of the first Arabian horse to be brought to New York. The broadside was published in March of 1805.
  Four hand-colored aquatints are from a drawing book printed and sold by William Charles, of Philadelphia, in 1815. The vignettes show a country cottage, a stone bridge, a country church, and an old mill. Each print has the name "Henry H. Krebs" inscribed along the top.
  George Ellis, a Philadelphia engraver, completed "The Peaceable Kingdom at the Branch," a popular view after Richard Westall, at only age sixteen.
  Henry Hoff, a lithographer and publisher, issued twenty "Views of New-York" in 1850. The colored lithographs were mounted onto decorative cards with a gold border and lettering. Eighteen of these views can be found here.
  Jacques-Gerard Milbert was a French naturalist and artist who traveled in the eastern United States from 1815-1823. Upon his return to France, he issued a portfolio, "A Series of Picturesque Views in North America, by J. Milbert, Corresponding member to the French Museum of natural history and several other scientific establishments, Paris, 1825." [from inscription on cover.] A complete set of the fourteen lithographs is rare; thirteen views and an original paper wrapper are held in this File. Several years later Milbert published more prints of America in a bound portfolio with two separate volumes of text; "Itineraire pittoresque du fleuve Hudson et des Parties laterals. L'amerique du nord." Titles on the prints, which were lithographed after drawings by Milbert, were rendered in French, English, Latin, and German. Fifty-three plates were issued; twelve can be found here. A version of Plate 40, without letters, was lithographed in New York in ca. 1821-1822 by Barnet & Doolittle, the first lithography firm in the United States.
  Paul Revere's print of the Boston Massacre, "The Bloody Massacre Perpetrated in King Street.. ." is one of the most famous American historical prints. He issued his print less than a month after the massacre, and it proved to be an important piece of visual propaganda for colonial Americans.
  Joseph Raskin's etchings show buildings at Harvard University, Princeton University, Amherst College, Williams College, Princeton University, and the University of Virginia.
  Caleb Ward's "View of the Spot where Gen. Hamilton fell at Weehawk" is extremely rare. It was first issued just after the erection of the monument in 1806, and then again in ca. 1830.
  James Abbott McNeill Whistler's "Twelve Etchings from Nature," are predominantly views of the French countryside, but also include several urban scenes.
  The Woodcut Society, an organization for print enthusiasts that existed between 1932 and 1952, published two prints a year. Eight of these prints can be found in this File.
  Prints are filed alphabetically in boxes. Prints by Henry Hoff, Jacques Gerard Milbert, and those published by the Woodcut Society are housed in their own boxes.
  - Abel, Carl
    - Four line engravings of a farmhouse, meadow, and brook, undated
    - Two line engravings of the ocean, undated
  - Adams, Wayman, 1883-1959
    - [African American woman and two children], undated
      General note
      lithograph
  - Baker, John, fl. 1832-1835
    - "The Return", undated
      engraving
  - Bianco, Pamela, b. 1906
    - [Geraniums], ca. 1930-1939
  - Blamney, Helen Farley, 1849-1902
    - [Cottage by lake with moon], 1889
      etching
  - Browne, Syd, b. 1907
    - "The Palisades", 1939
      engraving, impression 2 of 50
  - Bry, Edith, 1898-1991
    - "Dusk", undated
      lithograph, 2 copies, impressions 20 and 24 of 25
    - "Aged", undated
      lithograph, impression 3 of 20
    - [Two nuns], undated
      lithograph, impression 2 of 20
    - "Devout", undated
      See also: Series II
  - Bufford, John Henry, 1810-1870
    - [Views of the Adirondack Mountain Region], (New York: 1838)
      - "Rossie Lead Vein"
      - "View of the Indian Pass"
        after Charles Cromwell Ingham, 1796-1863
      - "View of the Adirondack Mountains Mt. Marcy Mt. McIntyre"
        after Ebenezer Emmons, 1799-1863
      - "Trap Dyck, at Avalanche Lake"
        after Charles Cromwell Ingham
      - "View at Lake Colden"
      - "Distant View of Mt. Marcy"
        after Ebenexer Emmons
      - "View of Mt. McMartin"
      - "View of the Indian Pass, from Lake Henderson"
      - "View of the Dial Mountain"
      - "Map of the Tertiary of Essex Co."
        engraved by George W. Merchant, 1789 or 90-1843
      - "Mining District of Rossie"
        engraved by George W. Merchant
      - "Falls of the Genesee"
      - "Section from the Mouth of the Genesee River to Instantur Penn"
      - "Geology of the Genesee River"
      - "Vertical Section showing Relative Thickness of the Different Rocks"
  - Burgis, William, fl. 1716-1731
    - "View of Fort George", 1730-1731
      hand-colored mezzotint
    - "View of the New Dutch Church", 1731
      See also: Series III
  - Burnet, S.
    - "The Celebrated Arabian Horse Grand Seignior", 1805
      broadside illustrated with woodcut, printed by John Tiebout, New York
  - Carwitham, John, fl. 1723-1741
    - "A View of Fort George with the City of New York from the S. W.,", after 1764
      hand-colored line engraving, printed for Carrington Bowles, London, [date pictured ca. 1731]
  - Charles, William, 1776-1820
    - Four hand-colored aquatint vignettes from a drawing book, [1815]
  - Church, Frederick Stuart, 1842-1924
    - [Woman with bird], 1887
  - Cole, Timothy, 1852-1931
    - "Mrs. Graham, [after] Gainsborough", 1930
      on tissue
    - "Broken pitcher, [after] Greuze", 1907
    - "Frag. Feliz Ortensio Palavicino by El. Greco, Boston Art Museum", 1930
    - "Princess Cattaneo by Van Duyck", 1930
    - [Mona Lisa], 1914
    - [After Eugene Carriere], 1909
  - Darley, F. O. C. (Felix Octavus Carr), 1821-1888
    - Five small vignettes
    - Title plate from Illustrations of the Legend of Sleepy Hollow
    - "Four Seasons", 1869
      foldout from Art Supplement to Appleton's Journal
  - Dwight, Theodore, Jr., 1796-1866
    - Six lithographs, views of the Hudson River, Catskills, and Hudson River Valley., undated
      Several copies of each, some hand-colored.
  - Ellis, George B., fl. 1821-1838
    - "The Peaceable Kingdom of the Branch", 1819
      engraving after Richard Westall, 1765-1836
  - Gayler, Julian F., 1872-1948
    - "Peacock" [Grounds of Grenville L. Winthrop House, Lenox, Massachusetts], [1936]
    - "House of Lenox Mass 1936" [Winthrop House, designed by Gayler]
    - [Old House Near East Haddam Connecticut], 1938
    - [Old Mill Western Massachusetts], 1935
  - Glover, De Lay, ca. 1823-ca. 1863
    - "The Summer Dream", undated
    - "The Empty Cradle", undated
    - "The Evening Star", undated
    - [William Shakespeare], undated
    - [Oliver Goldsmith?], undated
    - [two untitled scenes, two untitled portraits, a printer's trade card, and two vignettes], undated
  - Grant, Gordon, 1875-1962
    - "Fog Over Gloucester", undated
  - Gross, Chaim, 1904-1991
    - [Design to commemorate the 100th anniversary of laying the cornerstone of Central Synagogue in New York City], 1971
      lithograph, impression 22 of 120
  - Haskell, Ernest, 1876-1925
    - Birth announcement of Haskell's daughter Hildegarde, 1910
    - Greeting Card, undated
    - Holiday Card, undated
    - "In memorium" for Elizabeth Louise, Haskell's first wife, undated
    - Wedding announcement for Haskell's second marriage to Emma Loveland, 1920
    - Birth announcement for twins Ernest jr. and Josephine, 1921
  - Henry, J.
    - "Water Mill" [Nyack], 1880
  - Heriot, George, 1766-1844
    - [Bordeaux, France], after 1816
      aquatint
  - Hoff, Henry
    - "Views of New-York," 1850, color lithographs
      - "Astor Place Theatre"
      - "University" [Washington Square]
      - "Niblo's Hotel"
      - "Grace Church"
      - "Union-Square, Bird's Eye View"
      - "Stewart's Buildings and Broadway"
      - "New-York from Governor's Island"
      - "City Hall of Brooklyn"
        after C. Autenrieth
      - "Castle Garden"
      - "Hospital of Brooklyn"
      - "Odd Fellows Hall"
      - "Croton Water Reservoir"
      - "City Hall"
      - "Tombs"
      - "Custom-House"
        after C. Autenrieth, published by Hoff & Bloede
      - "Exchange"
      - "Institution for the Blind"
      - "St. Paul's Church, Barnum's Museum and Astor House"
  - Kerr, Robert, 1823-ca.1904
    - "The Customs House, Wall Street, Viewed from Broad Street", 1845
      hand-colored lithograph after his own design, iew No. 1 in "Views of New-York by Robert Kerr, architect"
  - La Paglia, Anthony
    - "Seascape Series #3", [1930-1949]
      Colored woodblock print on mulberry paper. Impression 8 of 100.
    - "Landscape Series #2", [1930-1949]
      Colored woodblock print on mulberry paper. Impression 7 of 50.
    - "Landscape Series #3", [1930-1949]
      Colored woodblock print on mulberry paper. Impression 5 of 50.
    - [Snowscene], [1930-1949]
      Colored woodblock print on mulberry paper
    - [Still life], [1930-1949]
      Colored woodblock print on mulberry paper. Impression 21 of 37.
    - [Fish], [1930-1949]
    - [Birds], four different prints, [1930-1949]
  - Milbert, Jacques Gerard, 1766-1840
    - A Series of Picturesque Views in North America, Paris, 1825, lithographs
      - "1st View of McComb's Mill's on the River Harlem near King's Bridge"
      - "2nd View of the River Harlem"
      - "Mr. McComb's House on the River Harlem near King's Bridge"
      - "McComb's Bridge Avenue"
      - "View of the Tavern on the Road to King's Bridge near Fort Washington"
      - "Front View the Fortifications at Harlem near [the city of] New-York"
      - "Mr. Van Den Heuvel's Country Seat"
      - "Spiten Devil's Creek"
      - "View of Lydick's Mill & House on Bronx River, West Farms"
      - "Bridge on the Croton 40 Miles N. of New-York"
      - "View of the Fall on Bronx River Lydich's Mill West Farms"
      - "View of Flushing (Long Island), North America. Oak-trees, under which George Fox, quaker, preached the Truths of the Gospel"
        2 copies
      - "View of Flushing (Long Island), North America. Mr. Bowne's House. It remains in the possession of his family ever since 1661 time when it was built."
        3 copies
    - Itineraire pittoresque du fleuve Hudson et des Parties laterals. 1828-29.
      - "Interior of New-York, Provost Street and Chapel"
        lithography by Louis Villeneuve, figures by Victor Adam, Plate 3
      - "Tarry-town where Major Andre was Captured"
        lithography by Louis-Philippe-Alphonse Bichebois, figures by Victor Adam, Plate 4
      - "Sing-Sing or Mount Pleasant"
        lithography by Leon Sabatier, figures by Victor Adam, Plate 5
      - "Haverstraw or Warren Landing"
        lithography by Louis-Philippe-Alphonse Bichebois, figures by Victor Adam, Plate 6
      - "Lower Falls near the Residence of Mrs. Montgomery"
        lithography by Louis Villeneuve, figures by Victor Adam, Plate 10
      - "Town of Hudson"
        lithography by Leon Sabatier, Plate 11
      - "View of Hudson & the Catskill Mountains"
        lithography by Louis-Philippe-Alphonse Bichebois, figures by Victor Adam, Plate 12
      - "Albany-Capital of the State of New-York"
        lithography by Isidore-Laurent Deroy, Plate 13
      - "The Spot where General Burgoyne surrendered to General Gates"
        lithography by Leon Sabatier, figures by Victor Adam, Plate 17
      - "General View of the Hudson at Adley's"
        lithography by Louis-Julien Lacottet, figures by Victor Adam, Plate 29
      - "Falls on the Genesee Rivers"
        lithography by Francois-Joseph Dupressoir, figures by Victor Adam, Plate 37
      - "Military Post. Sacketts Harbor"
        lithography by Jean Louis Tirpenne, figures by Victor Adam, Plate 39
      - [Black River Near Lake Ontario]
        lithography by Barnet & Doolitt, Plate 40 [ca. 1821-1822]
      - "Machine for the Portage on the Susquehanna"
        lithography by Leon Sabatier, Plate 51
  - Nelson, George Laurence, 1887-1978
    - [Still life], 1942
      lithograph presented to members of the Allied Artists of America
  - Newton, Edith, 1878-1964
    - "Marion's Dolls", 1937
  - Noual, J., fl. 1761 to late 18th century
    - "A View of Bethlehem, one of the Brethren's Principal Settlements, in Pennsylvania, North America,", undated
      hand-colored line engraving after Nathaniel Garrison, printed for Robert Sayer, London
  - Northcote, Stafford M.
    - "Tong Yin Yee Schung Gun", undated
      proof wood engraving, after his own design, printed on tissue
  - Pendleton's Lithography, William S. and John B. Pendelton
    - "The Toilet", undated
    - "Henry Costar's Hat Warehouse", 1831
      drawn by A. J. Davis
  - Pennell, Joseph, 1860-1926
    - [Streetscape], undated
  - Perard, Victor, 1870-1957
    - "Sketch Class, Provincetown Mass.", 1940
    - "Tending Nets, Cape Cod Mass.", 1941
  - Prang, Louis, 1824-1909
    - Lithographs after Winslow Homer, from Campaign Sketches, 1863
      - "The Letter for Home"
      - "Foraging"
      - "Our Jolly Cook"
  - Raskin, Joseph, 1897-[1981]
    - "Amherst College", undated
    - "Blair Hall, Princeton University", undated
    - "Campbell Hall, Princeton University", undated
    - "The Chapel, Amherst College", undated
    - "Chapin Hall, Williams College", undated
    - "The Converse Hall, Amherst College", undated
    - "Griffin Hall, Williams College", undated
    - "Memorial Hall, Harvard University", undated
    - "Princeton University", undated
    - "The Rotunda," University of Virginia", undated
    - "Serpentine Wall, University of Virginia", undated
    - "Sever Hall, Harvard University", undated
    - "West College, Williams College", undated
    - "West Lawn, University of Virginia", undated
    - "Widener Library, Harvard University", undated
  - Revere, Paul, 1735-1818
    - "The Bloody Massacre Perpetrated in King Street Boston on March 5th 1770...,"
      hand-colored engraving
  - Roth, Ernest David, 1879-1964
    - "The South Side of the Inn at Buck Hill Falls", 1940
      published by Buck Hill Art Association
  - Sartain, John, 1808-1897
    - "Common Deer", 1830
      hand-colored line engraving after Thomas Doughty (1793-1856). Plate One from The Cabinet of Natural History and American Rural Sports: with Illustrations (Philadelphia: J & T. Doughty, 1830.)
  - Steeden, O.
    - Plates from Illustrations to Knickerbocker's History of New York (London: T. Palser, 1830) all engraved after Steeden's own design.
      - "Governor Stuyvesant Resolves to Defend his Horse"
      - "Dedrick Knickerbocker Chiding his Landlady for settling his room to rights"
      - "Squatters Arriving at a Fresh Settlement"
      - "Van Twiller and Council Met in Debate"
      - "The renowned Van Corlear, the Dutch Trumpeter"
      - "The Four Great Dutch Characters, Van Zant, Hardenbrock, Ten Broeken, and Van Courtland"
      - "Negro Servant Relating Tales to the Settlers"
      - "Dutch Cobbler Haranguing the Mob"
      - "Farm Yard Melody, or the Dutch Settler's Glory"
  - Sumner, H. F. & Co.
    - "Eleanor", 1833
      hand-colored, drawn by J. Penniman
    - "The Love Letter", 1833
      drawn by J. Penniman
  - Thienny?, G. A.
    - [Snow scene, with bridge over creek], undated
  - Wallace, William H.
    - "Along the Hackensack", undated
    - "Clean-Drinking Manor House, Maryland", undated
    - "Old School house, Tuckahoe Rd., Mt. Vernon", 1881
    - "Prison of Major Andre", undated
    - "Trees at Demorest", undated
  - Ward, Caleb
    - "View of the Spot where Gen. Hamilton fell at Weehawk [with a View of New York]", 1830
      Hand-colored aquatint after Jacob C. Ward, date depicted 1806.
  - Whistler, James Abbott McNeill, 1834-1903
    - "Twelve Etchings from Nature," printed in Paris, published in London by James A. Whistler, 1858, in original wrapper
      - "Liverdun"
      - "La Retameuse"
      - "En Plein Soleil"
      - "The Unsafe Tenement"
      - "La Mere Gerard"
      - "Street at Saverne"
      - "Little Arthur"
      - "La Vielle aux Loques"
      - "Annie"
      - "La Marchande de Moutarde"
      - "Fumette"
      - "The Kitchen"
  - Whitefield, Edwin, 1816-1892
    - "Lobelia Syphilitica", undated
      hand-colored lithograph by Lewis & Brown, New York, after drawings by Whitefield, illustration from Emma C. Embury's American Wild Flowers in Their Native Haunts (New York: D. Appleton & Co., 1845)
  - Wolf, Henry, 1852-1916
    - [Woman with two children], undated
      Inscribed to Samuel Shaw from Abbott Handerson Thayer (1849-1921)
  - Woodruff, Hale, 1900-1980
    - "African Headdress"
    - "By Parties Unknown"
    - "Coming Home"
    - "Giddap"
    - "Old Church"
    - "Relics"
    - "Sunday Promenade"
    - "Trusty on a Mule"
      Portfolio, 156 of 300, all linocuts dating from 1931-1940, printed in 1996
  - Woodcut Society, wood engravings published by
    - Buckland-Wright, John, 1897-1954, "The Forest Pool, 1939
    - Cheffetz, Asa, 1896-1965, "Midsummer Vermont", 1936
    - Cheffetz, Asa, 1896-1965, "Down Montgomery Way (Vermont)", 1940
    - Cook, Howard Norton, 1901-1980, "Eagle Dance", 1942
    - Landacre, Paul, 1893-1963, "Black Stallion, undated
    - Lathrop, Dorothy P. "Kou Hsiung", 1944
    - Leighton, Clare, b. 1899, "Winnowers Majorca", 1939
    - Lindsay, Lionel, b. 1874, "Repose", 1938